Guide to the History of Medicine Picture File, 1523-2002 and undated RL.00570
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- History of Medicine Picture File: Subjects Series, approx. 487 items
  - Caricatures, 26 items
    - France, chirurgien, Major, chargé de la santé du régiment, color lithograph, 18th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 2)
      Rotund military doctor in uniform walking in a hospital ward past groups of patients. Types militaires, Pl. 123, by Draner.
    - Consultation de médecins, 1760, by L. Boilly (1761-1845), matted color lithograph by Delpeck, Paris, between 1820-1830 [group of five aged doctors, all examining one another], box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Consultation de médecins, 1823, by L. Boilly, matted color lithograph by Delpeck, Paris, between 1820-1830 [group of five young doctors, all examining one another], box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - "A laudable partnership or Souls and Bodies cured without loss of Time (The cheapest Booth in the Fair)" by George N. Woodward, colored engraving, published 1795 September 3 [image of quack and partner hawking cures, with text of his speech to onlookers], box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 10)
    - Set of four Cruikshank caricatures: "Indigestion"; "The Blue Devils _!!"; "The Head ache"; "The Cholic"; one set of colored engravings, one set in black-and-white, published by Thomas McLean, 1835 August, 8 items; box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - Cartoons, 24 items
    - Color drawing of man pointing to his side, modern reproduction, Nuremberg, 17th century? (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Christ-like figure points to his upper abdomen, left side.
    - "Dr. Syntax with the Skimmington Riders," color engraving by Rowlandson, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Depicts the doctor on horseback, surrounded by a raucous crowd with pots, pans, and a drum, parading effigies through the street. Part of a series of engravings by Thomas Rowlandson titled "The Tours of Dr. Syntax."
    - "The doctor's dream," color engraving by Rowlandson, undated (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Dr. Syntax, asleep in a library, while small figures with books for wings fly above him.
    - "Irascible Patient. 'Does it hurt me?--Does that hurt you?,' " [patient grabbing doctor's nose], black-and-white engraving, Punch magazine, London, 1861 August 3 (Box 12, Folder 12)
      Caption above title: "The Doctor has been Sounding the Gentleman's Chest in the present Approved Fashion: ie., without giving him previous notice."
    - Society of Pithotomists, black-and-white engraving, circa 1897 [Young chubby child as Asclepias/Bacchus astride barrel of drink, flanked by cat and owl] (Box 12, Folder 12)
      According to note, drawing is by Max Brödel, medical illustrator and member of the Pithotomy Club at Johns Hopkins Hospital. The Pithotomy Club was an eating club. The drawing represents the birth of a new doctor (infant with wings), accompanied by learning (hat) and wisdom (owl). Pithos means "keg," otomy, "opening." Gift of James Semans, member of the Pithotomy Club.
    - French illustrations of minor maladies and accidental injuries, hand-colored engravings, circa early 1800s, 12 items (Box 12, Folder 13)
      Small hand-colored French line engravings feature vignettes of individuals in open or indoor settings, in the throes of an illness or an injury. Scenes illustrate the dangers of accidental amputations, dog bites, bee stings, an ankle injury, burns, toothache, indigestion, and poisoning, among others. Images measure 3 1/4 x 3 5/8 inches. Originally formed part of a larger broaside titled "Le medecin a la maison ou conseils utiles pour secourir les blessés et guérir tous les accidens," a series of 24 illustrations by engravers Laguillermie and Rainaud, Paris.
    - "Esculape se mettant en garde pour defèndre...contre tous les novateurs blonds en noirs, qui viennent pour l'attaquer ["Hippocrate" as physician with giant hypodermic], 19th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Society of Pithotomists, 1897 [chubby child as Asclepius/Bacchus astride barrel of drink, flanked by cat and owl], black-and-white engraving, circa 1897, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "Amateurs excecutant une courante" [physicians in group playing "music" on medical devices], late 18th or early 19th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - The root of king's evil - n.b. to cure ye constitution of this evil, ye AXE must be laid to yet Root, color lithograph, England, 1835, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Shows a bewigged man in his study, reading a book open to an etymology of "radical," confronted with imp in the shape of a medicinal root, who holds up placards about reform, plunder, and showing two stakes through the Magna Carta and the Bible. Seems to refer to English politics and definition of radical reform.
    - The craft in danger [group of top-hatted men riding on and belaboring a mounted mega fauna fossil skeleton], matted lithograph by John Key, 1817, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 3)
      Penciled note indicates it is by John Key, 1817, on the proposal for a comparative anatomy course at Edinburgh University.
    - Il caso interessante [group of doctors examining leg of beautiful woman], matted color lithograph, Italy, by P. Folli, early 20th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - L'intervento chirurgico [group of surgeons in 18th century wigs, hacking apart a patient on operating table with cleavers, mallets, and saws], matted color lithograph, Italian, by P. Folli, early 20th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - "The Philadelphia physician-factory," by James Albert Wales, published in Puck, color lithograph mounted on board, 1880 April 14, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 20, Folder 11)
      Shows the "diploma mill" in action at Philadelphia Medical College, operated by "Professor Grind-em-out."
    - Modern medical events, 1950 [humorous poster of history of medicine in North America] (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Cemeteries, 1 item
    - "Another form of mortsafe in Greyfriars Churchyard, Edinburgh," black-and-white photograph, early 20th century (Box 12, Folder 14)
  - Chemistry, 6 items
    - Historical medical apparatuses from the London Science Museum: a chart (Dalton's elements), and one diagram, "Chrysopoeia," undated, modern black-and-white photographs, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Childbirth, 5 items
    - Illustration from "Rosegarten," a work by Eucharius Rösslin [midwife seated on stool examining patient in birth chair], modern black-and-white photograph of 1513 engraving (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Illustration from Della commare, Girolamo Mercurio, modern black-and-white photograph of engraving depicting Caesarean section, circa 1642 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Physician seated on stool assisting birth, with two female attendants, consultation of stars in background, modern photograph of black-and-white engraving from circa 17th century (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - "Post T[H]amar geminos vitales aedit in auras possitur ad poenas sic stat sententia Iudae," black-and-white engraving [Dutch?] [bedchamber of woman who just gave birth to twins, surrounded by female attendants], 17th century?, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 4)
      After the work by Martin Heemskerck, 16th century painter, representing Biblical story of Judah and Tamar, birth of Pharez and Zarah. The creator could also be the painter himself.
    - "Birth of St. Edmund," color lithograph, 19th century, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 4)
      Reproduction of medieval illustration of bedchamber after birth; H. Shaw, lithographer.
  - Circumcision, 3 items
    - "Ceremonie de peuples de Guinée pour la circoncision d'un enfant," black-and-white engraving, 1700s? (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Tribesmen with spears standing in a semi-circle around a woman holding the hand of a small boy; a snake is in the foreground.
    - "Die Beschneidung Christi," hand-colored engraving of clergy circumcising infant Christ, undated (Box 12, Folder 16)
      Number 52 of an edition of 187.
    - "Die Beschneidung Christi," St. Gilgen circumsising the infant Christ, painted by Pacher, circa 1932, black-and-white print illustration (Box 12, Folder 16)
  - Embryology, 2 items
    - Seven different stages of the embryo, undated, black-and-white modern photograph of an engraving (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Embryo, illustration from De integritatis et corruptionis virginum motis, Severinus Priaeus (d. 1619), black-and-white engraving, 1639, (box size: 18.5 x 24 inches) (Box 17, Folder 16)
      "I. Roulliard, 1597 edition" is also noted on the back.
  - History of Medicine, 29 items
    - Man, Medicine, and Work, U.S. Department of Health, Education and Welfare, 1963, 1 item (Box 12, Folder 18)
      Federal publication in pamphlet form, detailing historic events in occupational medicine.
    - Set of six colored engravings illustrating illnesses, treatments, physicians, and hospitals or sick rooms, by Clemens Kohl, engraver, before 1807, 8.25x10 inches (Box 12, Folder 19)
      Six engravings feature 19 vignettes, with some engravings featuring one scene, and others usually featuring two. One engraving features 12 small frames, each with a patient suffering from an illness.
    - Stages in the growth of modern medicine, black-and-white postcards and mini-essays from The Wellcome Historical Medical Museum, 20th century, 10 items (Box 12, Folder 20)
  - Hospitals, 13 items
    - "Lugduni Batavorum, apud Phillippum Bonk, 1744," [anatomical man lying on table], black-and-white engraving, 1744? (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - "Krankensaal im Hôtel-Dieu," and "Miniature aus dem Livre de la vie active des Religieuses de l'Hôtel-Dieu" in Paris, 15 Jahrhundert, two black-and-white engravings from book, undated (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - "Arms of the Foundling Hospital" and "Several children of the Foundling Hospital," two black-and-white engravings from a book page, 1809 (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - Photographs of book opened to "Mater misericordia," illustration featuring two clergymen looking up to image of Virgin Mary, six modern black-and-white photographs taken in library setting, possibly Trent Room at Duke, 20th century, 8 items (Box 12, Folder 21)
      Photographs are taken from different perspectives.
    - Patients lying prone on hospital beds while working machinery, one page from book with two black-and-white photographic reproduction images, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 21)
    - The good Samaritan, John Boydell, black-and-white engraving, 1772 (Oversize-folder 1)
      From a painting by William Hogarth that reportedly hangs at St. Bartholomew's Hospital.
  - Infant Care, 3 items
    - "L'accouchée, vâ laver son enfant dans la rivière," [the new mother washes her infant in the river], black-and-white engraving, circa 1780s (Box 12, Folder 22)
    - Child's metal cup with cover, undated, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 22)
      (2 copies)
  - Leeches, 2 items
    - The Leech Museum, ceramic plate illustrated with various implements, undated, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 23)
    - The Leech Museum, ceramic urn emblazoned with the word "leeches," undated, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 23)
  - Manikins, 51 items
    - Female [ivory?] anatomical manikins, modern black-and-white photographs, 18 items (Box 12, Folder 24)
      The photographs range in size from 2x3 to 8x10 inches. All seem to be manikins in the Trent Collection at Duke.
    - Ivory anatomical manikins collection, modern slide, negatives, 18 items (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Ivory Janus figure, half woman and half skeleton, 17th century?, modern black-and-white photograph (side view), slides, negatives, 7 items (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Head of wax anatomical manikin, close-up, University of Florence, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "Sala del sistema osseo e muscolare," human anatomical figures room at the University of Florence, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "Gemmelli dicoriali," wax manikin embryos of twins, University of Florence, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - "Statua femminile giacente," female wax manikin, University of Florence, modern color postcard (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Anatomical manikin, male, abdominal plate open, modern color photograph, 2 x 3 inches (Box 12, Folder 24)
    - Nkisi Nkondi [West African human fetish figure], modern black-and-white photographs, undated, 3 items (Box 12, Folder 24)
  - Medical Costumes, 2 items
    - "2300 years of medical costumes, by Abbott Laboratories", circa 1950s (2 copies), box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 6)
      Published set of nine color prints; note states "by Swiss illustrator Warja Honegger-Lavater, from authentic replicas in the Univ. of Rome's Institute of Medical History."
  - Medical Devices, 6 items
    - Early monocular slide viewer, similar to microscope, with ivory handle and strip of mounted objectives, 18th century?, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 25)
      Two copies, 8 x 10 inches. Item is in History of Medicine Artifacts Collection at Duke.
    - Medical instruments of various kinds, four prints, circa 19th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Medicine Chests, 3 items
    - Wooden medicine chest, 1800-1820, black-and-white photographs, undated (Box 12, Folder 26)
      The chest is from the Trent Collection at Duke. Three 8 x 10 inch photographs from different angles show the open wooden chest, along with scales, bottles, and home medical manual.
  - Military Medicine, 3 items
    - "Embarkation of the sick at Balaklava," color lithograph, published in England, hospital seen in distance on slope, 1855, box size: 18.5 x 24 inches (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - "Officers and nurses, Base Hospital, Camp Greene, Charlotte, N.C.," large panoramic photograph, circa 1919, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 6)
      World War I-era group photo of approx. 100 individuals, equal numbers of men and women. Photographer's name - "A. F. Orr, Old Town, Me [Maine]." Includes slide.
  - Natural Science, 4 items
    - "Canis rabiosus" [rabid dog], engraved illustration, 17th century?, modern black-and-white photograph (Box 12, Folder 27)
      Includes negative.
    - "The compleat angler or the contemplative man's recreation...," watercolor by R. A. Mersino, 1994, design based on Izaak Walton's book cover from 1676, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - "Fossil turtle, in a nodule of Harwich cement-stone, showing an internal view of the carapace. Drawn from the original in the collection of Edward Charlesworth, Esq...," lithograph, 1836 January, box size: 23 x 30 inches (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - Nurses and Nursing, 15 items
    - Two nurses in uniform, Richmond Photograph Company, albumen portrait photograph, late 19th century, 5 x 7 inches (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Cabinet card.
    - "A trained nurse" [nurse in uniform carrying a dinner tray], color frontispiece from In Sickness and in Health Manual, J. Roosevelt, 1896 (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - Nurse in uniform by man's bedside, with view of room, black-and-white engraving, 19th century, modern photograph reproduction, 5 x 7 inches (Box 12, Folder 28)
    - "Un bureau de norrices" [wet-nurses' "office"], from Hygiène et mèdicine des deux sexes, black-and-white engraving by Duesnes, drawing by P. Kauffman, circa 1885 (Box 12, Folder 28)
      Shows the outer doors of a French establishment offering the services of wet-nurses, two of whom are seated with infants on benches under windows with the signs "Nourrices sur lieux" and "Nourrices de province." A woman in elegant street clothes stands nearby, talking to a wet-nurse.
    - Nurses' costumes through the centuries, from 1242 to 1925, with captions, stamped on back "Duke University School of Nursing," set of color prints, circa 1930s, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches; 7 items (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Operating Rooms, 1 item
    - Views of early 20th century surgeon in uniform, surgeon's mask, and operating room, modern black-and-white images on card mount (Box 12, Folder 29)
    - "The Gross Clinic, 1875," scene from surgical theater, Jefferson Medical College, color reproduction of painting, 20th century, box size: 20x24 inches (Box 21, Folder 6)
      Copy of this reproduction also in box 17, folder 1, under "Gross, Samuel David."
  - Pediatrics, 6 items
    - "Soll sich der Arzt dir hülfreich zeigen" [sick child and doctor], black-and-white engraving, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - "Der kleine Patient" [sick child and doctor], Rohmburg, black-and-white engraving, early 19th century? (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - "Maladie vénérienne chez l'enfants" [sick child and doctor in hospital room with onlookers], black-and-white engraving, from Hygiène et Médecine de deux sexes, 19th century (Box 12, Folder 30)
      Title comes from penciled note on page from book with illustration. Title under illustration states that heroic doctor, who seems to be performing mouth-to-mouth resuscitation, died "for an unknown child."
    - "Der Dorfarzt" [doctor with child and woman], by Fisher, black-and-white engraving, 1858 (Box 12, Folder 30)
      Village physician in his consulting room with a woman holding a little boy; bundles of herbs hang from the ceiling. Illustration is from Cosmorama oder dei..., Zurich.
    - "Der Chirurgus" [doctor operating on a boy's knee], small colored engraving, 18th century? (Box 12, Folder 30)
    - The compleat pediatrician: practical, diagnostic, therapeutic - and preventive pediatrics, 1940, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 9)
      Color title page in mat of third edition of work by Wilburt C. Davison, Professor of Pediatrics, Duke University, 1940, adapted from Izaak Walton's Compleat Angler, 1653.
  - Pharmacies, Pharmaceutical, 2 items
    - Interior of 18th-century apothecary's laboratory/kitchen, with apothecary at work and woman servant at sink, black-and-white reproduction of painting or illustration, 20th century (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - China and glass serving pieces, 19th century?, modern color photograph (Box 12, Folder 31)
      Ruby glass stemmed cups of various sizes, ruby glass dispenser (sugar?), small oval china serving plate, and silver spoon. Probably pharmaceutical set. May be in Trent Collection at Duke.
  - Physicians, 37 items
    - "Dieu gueri le paralitique," black-and-white engraving, J. Honn[--], 18th century? (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - "Der Tod und der Doctor," [Skeleton handing wine flask to doctor], woodcut, 17th century? (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Interior view of [18th century Dutch?] physician's office with woman patient gesturing to her breast, black-and-white photographic reproduction of painting, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - "Die kranke Frau," [The sick lady] engraving by W. French, from painting by Netscher, 1664?, reproduction on cardstock, undated (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Woman in fur-trimmed jacket and gown is seated in bed-chamber, doctor in fur-trimmed coat and hat stands near her with his fingers on her pulse, gazing into an upheld flask, while a female servant in the background parts a bedcurtain. Date engraved on edge of tray with quill.
    - "La maladie," Death as a skeleton in robes stands over a physician writing at desk with medical instruments, engraving, 19th century (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Reproductions on single page of two 19th century photo portraits of Dr. Emily Blackwell, New York physician; 19th-century doctor Agnes Hockaday with child and parents; and a view of children's ward in Minnesota Northwestern Hospital for Women and Children, with nurse cradling a child, 20th century (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Single page with four black-and-white reproductions of 19th century photographs. Cut from jacket of book, "Send Us A Lady Physician: Women Doctors in America 1835-1920," 1986
    - "Grandeur d'âme d'Alexandre, envers son médecin Philippe" [Alexander the Great lying in bed-chamber with empty cup in hand, looking at his physician Philippos], by Le Seur, reproduction of engraving from German publication, 1911 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Engraving is from original by Italian Carracci. Page title is Bildersammlung aus der Geschichte der Medizin, from Kunstbeilage 65 zur Deutschen Medizinischen Wochenschrift 1911, no. 18.
    - "Ascultating the Gibson Girl" [Cupid with stethoscope listens to Gibson Girl's heartbeat], from Life Magazine, small photo reproduction of black-and-white engraving, 1901 (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Information about image is taken from penciled note.
    - Gustav von Bergmann (1878-1955), University of Berlin, with large group of men in lab coats in classroom theater seating, flanked by two women (a nurse and administrator?), black-and-white photograph, circa 1930s (Box 12, Folder 32)
      Penciled note on back says "Prof. G. v. Bergmann."
    - Document for six-percent loan of $1400.00 to the Sunbury and Erie Railroad Company issued by City of Philadelphia in the name of noted obstetrician Charles Delucena Meigs,1855 January 24, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 11)
      Mounted on board. Bears detailed engraved borders and illustrations: the Philadelphia State House, oval portraits of George Washington, Benjamin Franklin, and other men, and vignettes of docks, a locomotive, and workers. Signed by the City Controller and Treasurer.
    - "An itinerant doctor at Tien-Sing, China," color engraving by P. Lightfoot, 1840 (Box 12, Folder 33)
      Fisher, Son, & Co., London.
    - "Doctor's life," series, distributed by Armour Laboratories, 12 color prints of scenes depicting events in the lives of physicians, circa 1930s, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 12)
      Scenes from a doctor's life, from paintings by medical illustrator Frank Netter, include an emergency ward, cramming for exams, a new private practice, an anatomy lab, an African American home birth, a pediatric ward in a hospital, an ambulance call, a clinic with working-class patients, on the scene at a fire, and others.
    - "Surfeyte, age, and sickenes, are enemyes all to health, Medicines to mende the body excell all worldly wealth...," page with black-and-white engraving with verses from Bullein's Bulwarke of defence ainst all sicknesse..., 17th century?, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Engraving shows physician standing with staff, a skull and a bone lie beside his foot, with verses underneath by William Bullein, English physician and cleric (c. 1515-1576).
    - Physician, probably Laennec, inventor of the stethoscope, examining a patient, modern reproduction of painting, 20th century, box size: 11.5 x 15 inches (Box 14, Folder 13)
      Photographic reproduction of large painting. Partially visible label on frame of painting reads "-ec À L'Hopital Necker" (referring to Hopital Necker-Enfants Malade, Paris).
    - "Physick, from the original picture of the same size painted by Ostade...", color engraving, England, 1763 [portrait of Renaissance-era physician], box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
      Includes slide reproduction.
    - "Fuscus-eques medicus rhetor dux..." [image of physician], black-and-white engraving mounted on board, England, William Browne, 1771, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "Le médecin clairvoyant," by Belman, black-and-white engraving after painting, 1775, box size: 16.5 x 20.5 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Postage stamp with image of Greek statue of physician[?], undated, modern black-and-white close-up photo, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - "Beaumont and St. Martin," color print reproduction of painting by Dean Norwell, 20th century, box size: 16x20 inches (Box 16, Folder 6)